Guide to the Burd-Shippen Family Papers, 1717-1898 DAR.1966.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Burd-Shippen Family Papers
1717-1898
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Burd family
Shippen family
DAR.1966.01
1.25 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
The Burd and Shippen families were prominent lawyers, business owners, and public servants in eastern Pennsylvania during the colonial era. The Burd-Shippen papers contain personal and business correspondence, legal documents, business records, and manuscripts. Many of the legal documents and business records pertain to both Edward Burd and Edward Shippen's legal practices as well as their positions in Pennsylvania government. Digital reproductions are available online for contents in Series V.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of the contents of Series V are available online.
Biography
The Shippen family traces their lineage back to Edward Shippen I (1639-1712), a Quaker who moved to Philadelphia from Boston in 1693. Edward Shippen I's great-great-grandson, Edward Shippen III (1703-1781), had three children: Edward Shippen IV (1729-1806), Sarah Shippen (1731-1784), and Joseph Shippen (1732-1810).
Edward Shippen IV, a wealthy and prominent lawyer in Philadelphia, held multiple public offices by royal appointment. He fathered six surviving children, including Elizabeth Shippen (1754-1828) and Margaret "Peggy" Shippen (1760-1804). During the American Revolution, Edward Shippen IV lost his appointments, yet managed to keep his family financially afloat by remaining politically neutral. Both of his daughters married American revolutionaries. Elizabeth married her cousin, Edward Burd (1751-1833), while her younger sister, Peggy, married Benedict Arnold.
Sarah Shippen married James Burd (1726-1793) in 1748. A Scotsman by birth, James Burd commanded Fort Augusta during the French and Indian War, rising to prominence afterwards as a merchant and colonial magistrate. Their son, Edward Burd (1750/51-1833), served as a major in the Revolutionary War. Following the war, he was prothonotoray and later justice of the Supreme Court of Pennsylvania. Edward Burd was a friend and business associate to his uncle and father-in-law, Edward Shippen IV. Edward Burd wrote Neddie Burd's Reading Letter, a history of the Berks County bar.
Elizabeth Shippen and Edward Burd had one son, Edward Shippen Burd (1779-1848). He married watercolorist Eliza Howard Simms (1793-1860) and resided in Philadelphia, where he worked as an attorney specializing in property law. Edward Shippen Burd was also involved in real estate and business ventures, including the Philadelphia Arcade and the Philadelphia Ice Company. He was a member of the American Philosophical Society, and, with his wife, donated extensively to philanthropic projects, particularly St. Stephens Church and the Protestant Episcopal Hospital of Philadelphia.
The Burd-Shippens are related to the Hubley and Walker families. Edward Burd Hubley, (1792-1856) a lawyer from Reading, Pennsylvania, served the Twenty-fourth and Twenty-fifth Congresses as a representative from Pennsylvania. He later became a canal commissioner of Pennsylvania and then a commissioner of Cherokee affairs.
Scope and Content Notes
The majority of the collection includes the personal correspondence and business records of Edward Burd and, his relative, Edward Shippen IV. The business papers include legal documents such as deeds and indentured servant lists, business records in the form of invoices and receipts, and correspondence concerning debts and legal matters. The papers also relate to members of the Burd and Shippen families such as Sarah Shippen Burd, Elizabeth Burd, Edward Shippen Burd, James Burd, and James Burd Hubley. The collection contains the papers of Lewis Burd Walker, an amateur historian and family genealogist. Included in Lewis Burd Walker's papers are transcriptions of the wills of Margaret Shippen Arnold and Benedict Arnold. Walker also provides transcriptions of letters written by Margaret Shippen Arnold to family and friends.
Arrangement
The papers have been arranged in five series, reflecting family and business correspondence of the Burds and Shippens, as well as general correspondence with and between extended family. A final series has been added for the papers of family genealogist and amateur historian Lewis Burd Walker, which relate to the Burd-Shippens.
Series I. Family Correspondence, 1777-1869
Series II. Burd Family Business Papers, 1774-1855
Series III. Shippen Family Business Papers, 1717-1842
Series IV. General Correspondence, 1730-1806
Series V. Lewis Burd Walker Papers, 1823-1898
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Custodial History
This collection was located in the Darlington Memorial Library in the University's Cathedral of Learning until 2007 when it was moved to the ULS Archives Service Center for processing, storage, preservation and service. However, it remains in the custodianship of the ULS Special Collections Department.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased by the University of Pittsburgh from Emily Driscoll, a manuscript dealer, with Autographs and Manuscripts in New York City in 1966.
Previous Citation
Burd-Shippen Family Papers, 1717-1898, DAR.1966.01, Darlington Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Related Material
Burd-Shippen Papers, 1708-1792, B B892, American Philosophical Society.
Burd-Shippen Family Collection, 1715-1834, Manuscript group 30 Pennsylvania State Archives.
Burd Family Papers, 1703-1937, 379, University of Delaware, Special Collection Department.
Edward Shippen Burd, 1779-1848, MC 1999.10, Dickinson College, Archives and Special Collections.
Shippen Family Papers, 1750-1775, MG 375, New Jersey Historical Society.
Burd-Shippen Papers, 1750-1847, William L. Clements Library, The University of Michigan.
Bibliography
Klein, Randolph Shipley. Portrait of an Early American Family. University of Pennsylvania Press, Philadelphia: 1975.
Nixon, Lily Lee. James Burd, Frontier Defender. University of Pennsylvania Press, Philadelphia: 1941.
Burd, Edward. Neddie Burd's Reading Letter: An Epic of the Early Berks Bar. Berks County Bar Association, Reading, Pennsylvania: 1927.
Pennsylvania -- Genealogy; Family papers; Correspondence; Shippensburg (Pa.) -- History; Philadelphia (Pa.) -- History; Harrisburg (Pa.) -- History; Carlisle (Pa.) -- History; Lancaster (Pa.) -- History; Pennsylvania -- Politics and government; Pennsylvania -- History; Shippen, Edward; Burd, Elizabeth Shippen; Burd, James; Burd, Sarah Shippen; Arnold, Margaret Shippen; Arnold, Benedict; Pennsylvania. Supreme Court; Walker family; Donaldson family; Hubley family; Walker, Lewis Burd; Hubley, James Burd; Burd family; Shippen family; Burd, Edward; Burd, Edward Shippen; Shippen, Edward
- Family Correspondence, 1777-1869; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains correspondence between the Burd Family, Edward Burd and friends, the Hubley family, and the Shippen Family. It contains information about both the Burd and Shippen family genealogies. Much of the women's correspondence describes family affairs such as health issues, family meetings and household life after the Revolutionary War. The correspondence between the men is mainly in the form of business advice, inquiring about family members, and travel.
  - Edward Burd Domestic Correspondence, 1777-1823 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Edward Burd Domestic Correspondence, 1777-1823 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Edward Burd Correspondence, 1777-1821 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Edward Burd Correspondence, 1777-1821 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Edward Burd Correspondence, 1777-1821 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Edward Burd Correspondence, 1777-1821 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Edward Burd Correspondence, 1777-1821 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hubley Family Correspondence, 1788-1869 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hubley Family Correspondence, 1788-1869 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Hubley Family Correspondence, 1788-1869 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Hubley Family Correspondence, 1788-1869 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Hubley Family Correspondence, 1788-1869 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Hubley Family Correspondence, 1788-1869 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Hubley Family Correspondence, 1788-1869 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Sarah Burd Family Correspondence, 1790-1837 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Sarah Burd Family Correspondence, 1790-1837 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Margaret Coxe to Sarah Burd, 1816-1834 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Edward Burd from Jacob Hubley, 1818-1833 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Elizabeth Burd Family Correspondence, 1836-1845 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Burd Family Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Shippen Genealogy, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Edward Shippen from Cousin John, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Edward Shippen [Poem], undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Burd Family Business Papers, 1774-1855; II.
  The business papers of the Burd family feature receipts, legal documents, and correspondence of Edward and James Burd. Many of the letters are written from and to Philadelphia, and some are from other locations in eastern Pennsylvania including Lancaster and Carlisle. The materials also include some papers and correspondence of James Burd Hubley to Edward Burd and some of his legal documents. Within this portion of the collection, the majority of the documents are originals, however there are some hand-written drafts and copies mixed in as well which do not contain an official insignia or signature. Some documentation includes portions of letters in which both the composer and the addressee are unidentified, but one of the correspondents is presumably James Burd.
  - Edward Burd Legal, 1767-1811 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Edward Burd Legal, 1767-1811 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Edward Burd Legal, 1767-1811 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - [James Burd] to William Sherman, March 4, 1774 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - [James Burd] to a Brother, March 5, 1774 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - [James Burd], March 5, 1774 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Edward Burd Receipts, 1778-1796 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - William R. Atlee to Edward Burd, 1784-1792 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Thomas Duncan to Edward Burd, 1784-1799 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Thomas Duncan to Edward Burd, 1784-1799 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Thomas Duncan to Edward Burd, 1784-1799 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - E. Dutilh and Co. Transactions, 1784-1810 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - E. Dutilh and Co. Transactions, 1784-1810 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Alexander Foster to Edward Burd, 1786 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - George Davis to Edward Burd, 1786-1794 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Edward Crawford to Edward Burd, 1787-1798 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - David Grier to Edward Burd, September 3, 1789 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Samuel Caldwell to Edward Burd, 1790 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - W. Benezet to Edward Burd, September 11, 1790 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Thomas Buchanan to Edward Burd, September 22, 1790 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Samuel Benezet to Edward Burd, April 10, 1794 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Mrs. Bordley to Mr. Burd, May 1794 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Jared Ingersoll to Edward Burd, September 1, 1794 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - W. Grayson to Edward Burd, January 13, 1795 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Dutilh Family Business Correspondence, 1796-1806 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - John Caldwallader to Edward Burd, March 14, 1797 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Charles Adams to Edward Burd, May 24, 1797 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - W. Barton to Edward Burd, March 2, 1799 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Thomas Hamilton to Edward Burd, November 16, 1799 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Andrew Dunlap to Edward Burd, September 1, 1800 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - John Donaldson to Edward Burd, November 27, 1800 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Tarleton Bates to Edward Burd, January 3, 1801 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Joseph Burd to Jasper Yeates, April 10, 1803 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Henry B. Grubb to Edward Burd, May 20, 1804 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - John D. Heath to Edward Burd, July 27, 1805 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Robert Jackson to Edward Burd, October 25 1805 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - List of Debts due by the Estate of John Shippen, November 11, 1805 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - A.J. Dallas to Edward Burd, August 6, 1806 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Burd Family Receipts, 1808-1837 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - W.E.L. Burd to John F. Mifflin, December 7, 1812 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - James B. Hubley Business Correspondence, 1815-1855 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - James B. Hubley Business Correspondence, 1815-1855 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - James B. Hubley Business Correspondence, 1815-1855 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - James B. Hubley Business Correspondence, 1815-1855 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Thomas Caldwallader to Edward Burd, February 26, 1816 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Unknown to Edward Burd, February 9, 1817 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - C. Evans to Edward Burd, March 2, 1817 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Mrs. Allen to Edward Burd, undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - H. Brinton to Edward Burd, undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - B. Chew to Edward Burd, undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - M. Hare to Edward Burd, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
- Shippen Family Business Papers, 1717-1842; III.
  The Shippen family business papers include receipts, invoices and correspondence. Edward Shippen, a lawyer and judge, is the composer of a majority of the documents in this series. Many of the receipts refer to debts owed and paid to Edward Shippen and debts paid by him. There are invoices stating merchandise purchased by the Shippen family, such as coffee and meat. Letters and documents within this series contain legal documents pertaining to bonds, land ownership and tenants. It also contains business correspondence about land and debts owed from the Burd family to the Shippen family.
  - Shippen Family Receipts, 1717-1823 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Shippen Family Receipts, 1717-1823 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Edward Shippen Business Correspondence, 1718-1761 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Edward Shippen Legal, July 1719 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Shippen Family Business Accounts, 1728-1831 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Edward Shippen Bond Receipts, 1733-1769 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Samuel Storke and Sons to Edward Shippen, 1744-1745 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Edward Shippen Receipts, 1751-1770 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Edward Shippen Receipted Invoices, 1764-1765 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - James Burd to Edward Shippen, 1768-1782 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Shippen Family Business Correspondence, 1783-1842 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Joseph Shippen to John Wood, May 18, 1745 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Arrest warrant issued for Stephen Trancle by Edward Shippen, May 10, 1755 (Box 2, Folder 64)
- General Correspondence, 1730-1806; IV.
  General Correspondence refers to the letters and documents included within the Burd-Shippen Papers, which seemingly have little direct connection to either family, aside from geographic region. Some of the documentation makes reference to land deals, financial information, and social correspondence with distant relatives. These may represent some of Edward Shippen or Edward Burd's clients during their business or legal work.
  - Benjamin Hopkins to Captain, October 14, 1730 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - William Logan Receipts, 1740 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Cover Letter for Land Survey of Whippening, New Jersey, September 24, 1749 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Count Referees to Make Reports, Court of Carlisle, September 7, 1751 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Letter Drafts, 1766-1768 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Letters to Mrs. Yeates, 1770-1778 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Deed; John Webb and Benjamin Webb, April 3, 1774 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - George Smithers Order to Pay Joseph Nelson, January 25, 1775 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Sofia (Marsh) Burrow to E. D. Pietersoon, 1780 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Captain Burnham, Receipts and Orders, 1782-1786 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Thomas Connor Deed Poll, April 1, 1784 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - List of Jurors Struck, 1787 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Lands Surveyed in Northumberland County, October 15-25, 1792 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Charles Gallagher Case Evidence for Counterfeit Dollars, August 1794 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Joseph Duncan and Robert Walker Receipts, 1801-1806 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous Scribbling, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Lewis Burd Walker Papers, 1823-1898; V.
  Lewis Burd Walker's research about the Burd Family and the Arnold Family are within this series. Documentation includes transcripts of letters dating to 1823; though many letter transcripts have no original date on them. There are transcriptions of letters from Mrs. Margaret Shippen Arnold to her family and friends. Within the Letters and Papers of Lewis Walker is a transcript of the "Last Will and Testament of Benedict Arnold" and the "Last Will and Testament of Margaret Arnold." The papers also contain Lewis Burd Walker's hand-written manuscript of "A Few Glimpses of Our Little Peggy," a story about the life of Margaret "Peggy" Shippen Coxe.
  - Arnold Family Correspondence, 1780 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Lewis Burd Walker Letters and Papers, 1823-1897 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Lewis Burd Walker Letters and Papers, 1823-1897 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Lewis Burd Walker Letters and Papers, 1823-1897 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Letters and Papers of Lewis Walker, 1891-1898 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Letters and Papers of Lewis Walker, 1891-1898 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Letters and Papers of Lewis Walker, 1891-1898 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Letters and Papers of Lewis Walker, 1891-1898 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Transcripts, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Transcripts, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Transcripts, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Transcripts, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Transcripts, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Transcripts, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Transcripts, undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Transcripts, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Transcripts, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)